All right, thank you all for that,
for participating in that.
We're so thankful for this opportunity.
We're getting ready to wrap up our parable series.
Anybody challenged by the parable series
as much as I have been challenged by the parable series?
Okay, some of us, thank you, that's great.
I was, Gary, I was waiting for something.
I was like, Gary hasn't said something yet.
Is he here?
There he is, all right.
So we're wrapping up our parable series.
Next week, we are launching a series this summer
in the book of Psalms.
And Dr. Richter is actually gonna stay with us
after her seminar on Saturday
and launch our series on Psalms.
She has literally written a book on Psalms.
So you're gonna wanna be here.
You're gonna wanna bring your friends.
We're excited about that.
But this morning, we're wrapping up our parable series.
And remember, just as a recap,
the parables are aimed at stopping us in our tracks.
Their intent is to make us feel uneasy at first
as we wrestle with the story that Jesus is giving us,
the kingdom reality below that lesson.
And we've said that the parables
really have three main themes in them,
at least for our purposes in this series.
They introduce the surprising arrival of the kingdom,
that the kingdom of God is coming in unexpected ways,
in ways that the nation of Israel wasn't expecting,
in small, surprising ways,
like a seed planted in a field,
like lemon spreads through dough.
It's small and insignificant on the surface,
but it is unstoppable
as it gets a hold of the hearts
of those who have embraced God's kingdom.
It is a surprising arrival with a surprising ethic.
It demands sacrificial love and obedience.
It lays down our lives for those around us.
And because it's surprising in its arrival
and it's surprising in its ethic,
it presents us with a crisis of choice.
What will we do with the story of the kingdom of God?
Will we embrace it?
And will we live into it with our whole lives?
Or will we reject it?
Because those really are the only two choices.
I know in American Christianity,
we like to provide a third choice
where we can kind of be in and kind of be out,
one foot in, one foot out,
sitting on the fence, celebrating Jesus,
being a fan of Jesus,
but not really taking seriously, obeying Jesus.
And the parables just don't really give us that option, right?
That's what's kind of been so disconcerting for me
as we've studied these parables
is they really do not give us the option
of sitting on the fence.
You're either all in or you're all out.
Which will you choose is at the root of the parables
what Jesus wants us to be interacting with.
And so my prayer is that this series
has deepened our understanding of God's kingdom
and motivated us to view ourselves
as an answer to our own prayers.
When we pray, your kingdom come,
your will be done on earth as it is in heaven.
May we view that ourselves as we live into the kingdom
and answer to that prayer,
that we are participating with God
as he brings his kingdom on earth as it is in heaven.
So that's been the goal.
Hopefully that's landed in some way, shape, or form for you.
If not, send me an email and we'll talk about it.
Sound good?
All right, let's pray.
And we'll move into our last parable.
Father in heaven,
we thank you for the surprising arrival of your kingdom.
God, that you rode in on a donkey
to chants of Hosanna.
Everybody thinking the kingdom was coming in power
and it came in sacrificial love.
God, the kingdom came in such a surprising way
that the Son of God laid down his life for us.
And then the most unexpected plot twist
in all of human history
was not contained by that grave.
God, you rose from the dead.
Solidifying the reality of your kingdom
from now until you return.
God, in the ethic of your kingdom
is the same way that you established it.
It is sacrificial love.
It is laying down our life for our neighbors.
And that is a hard call.
But nothing on earth is worthy
of our time, attention, and resources
than that reality.
And so remind us of that this morning.
And God, for those of us who are wrestling
with the invitation to your kingdom,
for those of us that might find ourselves
on that fence with one foot in
and with one foot out,
or for those of us that have decided we're out,
we're not interested,
God, may this morning be an opportunity
for us to be re-invited
to embrace your kingdom fully.
Your glory for our neighbor's good.
In Jesus' name I pray, amen.
If you wanna follow along,
Matthew chapter 25 is where we're gonna get to.
Matthew chapter 25, starting in verse 14.
I don't know how many of you,
how good your memories are.
Raise your hand if you got a really good memory.
That's impressive, I'm so jealous of all of you
because I have a terrible memory,
especially when it comes to my childhood.
Like I try and think back
to some memories of my childhood
and I just don't have a lot
of vivid concrete memories.
I have lots of highlight clips, right?
Like I can roll some highlight clips
of my childhood playing around
in the backyard and all of those things.
But when it comes to concrete moments,
outside of the incredible things
that I did in peewee sports,
I have vivid memories of those.
But other than that, that was a joke, kind of.
We have a lot of home videos,
so it's less memories and more I've rewatched myself.
But anyway, that was not in the notes.
Okay, a few of my most concrete memories
are the first day that I went to public school.
I was homeschooled, kindergarten and first grade
and some of you are thinking,
okay, that makes sense.
I cannot spell and my mom makes fun of me for that
and then I remind her that she taught me to spell.
So there's that.
But I remember like the first time getting on a school bus,
the first time ushered into this big cafeteria
where everybody knew everybody except for me,
that was a really vivid memory.
Another one, the first drive I got to take in my car
on my own with nobody else.
I had this vivid memory of backing up my 1996 GeoTracker
and taking off to nowhere.
I wasn't even going anywhere.
I just wanted to go somewhere in the 96 GeoTracker.
Yes, I wish I still had that thing.
That thing was beautiful.
Four cylinders almost got up the hill.
I mean, we're 6,000 RPMs at 45 miles an hour
headed to church in Back Creek.
It was awesome.
And then one of the other ones is being left alone
at home for the very first time.
And I had an older brother,
so I always thought I was ready for things
before I actually was, right?
I watched him do all of these awesome things
and I'm like, I should be, I'm staying at home by myself.
My mom's like, no, you're not.
You're not.
But finally, I remember the time when it arrived,
when it was my opportunity to get to stay at home.
There was a tremendous amount of excitement
along with a little bit of unease
because I knew, like Donovan said,
it comes, or like Michelle said,
it comes with some responsibility.
It comes with some accountability, right?
If mom and dad come home and the house is in flames,
it's on me.
So as much as I longed for this freedom,
I also knew that it came with some responsibility
and some accountability.
And as we approach our parable this morning,
this is the backdrop that Jesus has for this parable,
that he's speaking to his disciples
as he is about to leave.
He is warning them that he is going,
that he is going to leave them here on purpose,
on a mission.
And this is a gift to them.
It is a gift to the world around them.
And it is a gift that comes with tremendous responsibility
and accountability.
And so as we approach this parable this morning,
I want us to think about that backdrop in our heads.
And let's go ahead and read Matthew chapter 25,
starting in verse 14.
Jesus tells this story.
He says, again,
the kingdom will be like a man going on a journey
who called his servants and entrusted his wealth to them.
He entrusted his wealth to them.
To one, he gave five bags of gold,
to another two,
and to another one bag each,
according to his ability.
Then he went on his journey.
The man who had received five bags of gold
went at once and put his money to work
and gained five bags more.
So also the one with two bags of gold money
went to work and gained two more.
But the man who had received one bag went off
and dug a hole in the ground,
and he hid his master's money.
After a long time,
the master of those servants returned
and settled accounts with them.
The man who had received five bags of gold
brought five more,
and he said,
Master, you have entrusted me with five bags of gold.
See, I have brought you five more.
His master replied,
Well done, good and faithful servant.
You have been faithful with a few things.
Also, this master and I need to meet
because five bags of gold
is not a few things in my economy,
but okay.
You've been faithful with a few things.
I will put you in charge of many things.
Come, share in your master's joy,
your master's happiness.
The man with two bags of gold also came.
Master, he said,
You entrusted me with two bags of gold.
See, I have gained two more.
His master replied,
Well done, good and faithful servant.
You have been faithful with a few things.
I will put you in charge of many things.
Come and share in your master's happiness.
Then, again, parables are hard, remember?
The man who had received one bag of gold came
and he said,
Master, I knew that you were a hard man,
harvesting where you have not sown
and gathering where you have not scattered seeds.
So I was afraid
and I went out and hid your gold in the ground.
See, here is what belongs to you.
His master replied,
You wicked and lazy servant.
So you knew that I harvested where I did not sow
and gather where I did not scatter seed.
Well then, you should have put my money
on deposit with the bankers
so that when I returned,
I would have received with it interest.
So take the bag of gold from him
and give it to the one who has 10 bags
for whoever has will be given more
and they will have an abundance
and whoever does not have,
even what they have will be taken from them
and throw that worthless servant
outside into the darkness
where there will be weeping and gnashing of teeth.
This is the word of the Lord.
Thanks be to God.
Yeah, it's a tough one
but I think if we give it the time it needs,
we should be able to walk out of here
more encouraged than discouraged.
Sound good?
Cool.
Last week, we covered one of Christ's final parables.
We're still in the final week of Christ's life
and he told three intentional parables
back to back to back
directly aimed at the corrupt Jewish leadership
which follows, that's Matthew 22,
which follows by Matthew chapter 24
which if I can be honest,
Matthew chapter 24 is one of the most difficult chapters
to understand in all of the New Testament.
So if you're bored this week,
have fun.
Send me some email.
No, don't.
Don't send me some email.
But I'll be honest with you,
I spent more time trying to understand Matthew 24
so that I could understand the context of this parable
than I did the parable itself.
Matthew 24 is extremely difficult.
But I think what I settled on
is ultimately what Jesus is doing
is after he tells these three parables
aimed at the Jewish leadership
and their corrupt nature
and he's saying,
this is your last chance to repent.
This is your last opportunity to come back.
And if you don't,
I'm going to take away your leadership.
I'm gonna take away your responsibility.
And so after this, chapter 24,
Jesus gives a shocking prediction.
He very clearly and prophetically prophesies
that the temple is going to be destroyed
before the disciples die.
He says,
this temple,
these stones,
they're gonna be ripped down.
These leaders who I just told these three parables against,
their leadership is going to be taken away
because they have not submitted to my kingdom.
And in shocking Jesus fashion,
you might be surprised to know,
it happened, right?
Rome comes in in 70 AD and destroys the temple
and the leadership no longer have any sway
over the nation of Israel.
It's all taken away from them.
This is a prediction that Jesus makes.
And so when he makes this prediction,
his disciples pull him aside,
slightly uncomfortable with chapter 24,
probably more uncomfortable with chapter 24 than I am.
And they ask him some questions.
What's going on here?
What do you mean?
They ask him,
when is this going to happen?
And how does this have to interact
with your coming again,
your second coming?
They use the language,
the end of the age.
The disciples likely thought
that if the temple was destroyed,
this would be the straw that broke the camel's back
and it would trigger the end of the age.
See, for 1,500 years,
all of worship of Yahweh was rooted
in the tabernacle and the temple.
With no temple and no priest,
worship would be impossible
and it almost would certainly usher
in God's rule and reign for all eternity.
And this is where it gets interesting
because Jesus responds by saying,
yes, the temple will be destroyed
in this generation,
but the second coming
and the destruction of the temple
are not connected.
As a matter of fact,
he very intentionally says
there's gonna be a long period of time
in between the destruction of the temple
and my second coming.
And he makes it very clear
that nobody knows
when the second coming is happening.
So if you spend time,
this is free, okay?
If you spend a lot of time on YouTube,
listening to people telling you
all about how Jesus is gonna come back soon
because of things that are happening
around the world,
Jesus says, don't worry about it.
You're wasting your time, okay?
He will return
and he might return tomorrow
and we should be anticipatory about that.
I'm not saying don't think about Christ coming,
think about Christ coming,
but don't try and figure out
when it's gonna happen
because he says nobody knows
when it's gonna happen.
So if your friend with 10,000 subscribers
on YouTube tells you
he knows when it's gonna happen,
listen, Jesus, red letters, okay?
No one's free.
And what he says is he says,
now when the temple is destroyed,
when the priest leadership is taken away,
the responsibility for true worship of Yahweh
will fall to you, the disciples,
and all who have embraced God's kingdom.
You will be priests.
We will be priests.
All of us who have embraced God's kingdom
will be priests.
We will carry forward the mission of God
and the worship of Yahweh
from Jerusalem to Judea,
to the ends of the earth.
This is what he's setting up with these parables.
He tells three parables
and they are directly aimed at his disciples,
directly preparing for them
for this period of time
after the destruction of the temple
and until his second coming returns.
So we've talked a lot
as we've read the parables.
We've said we need to understand them
in their original context
before we can understand them for ourselves.
And pretty much every parable
we've covered so far
was directed at a group of people
that are not us.
But I would argue that these parables,
more than any other parables,
are directed at a group of people
that are very similar to us.
He is directing these parables
to faithful followers of Jesus,
faithful followers of the kingdom
who are awaiting Christ's second return.
And so we can almost interpret these parables
as if they were written to us.
What will we do with what God has given us
as we await his return?
This is the overarching point of the parable.
And just like me being left at home
for the first time,
to me was a gift
of newfound freedom and responsibility.
It was a gift that came with responsibility
and accountability.
So too, Jesus says in this parable,
is me ascending into heaven,
sending the Holy Spirit to you
and entrusting you with the kingdom of God
until I return.
It is a gift
that comes with responsibility
and accountability.
And that is the overarching narrative
of this parable.
So let's unpack it one point at a time.
First, the gift.
A master gives his servants
an incredible amount of money.
Scholars debate exactly
over how much money each talent was.
Talent is just a number,
a metric of measurement.
Is that the right way to say that?
Metric of measurement?
Yeah?
Okay, cool.
We're gonna stick with it
because I don't know another way to say it.
And so some argue
one talent is somewhere between five and 20 years wages
for a normal worker.
So let's just say 1 million,
2 million,
5 million dollars, right?
It's a lot of money.
No matter whether you got the 1 million
or the 5 million,
you have been entrusted
with a massive gift,
a gift that servants of this time,
they would have been trusted
with these things.
And the master says,
I'm entrusting you
with this amount of wealth.
You get to steward it.
You get to use it.
Think of it as yours.
It is a gift.
Now,
the disciples hearing this parable
would have been way less pumped
about Jesus leaving them
than I was about my parents
leaving me at home alone.
Right?
The disciples are like,
Jesus,
no,
don't leave.
Why are you going?
You don't need to go.
You're here.
The Son of God is here.
The kingdom has come.
This is fine.
Let's do it this way.
But later in the Gospel of John,
Jesus tells his disciples
very clearly,
it is better
that I go
so that the Holy Spirit
can come.
Jesus leaving
after his resurrection
and ascending into heaven
is a gift
and we have to see it that way.
We have to view it that way
because if not,
we will miss out
on the things
that we've been entrusted with.
Not only does he tell the disciples
it's better that I go
that the Spirit can come
but what is increasingly becoming
two of my favorite chapters
in all of the Bible,
Revelation chapter four and five
show that Jesus
is actually actively
doing something in heaven
bringing about
his final restoration.
Jesus needed to ascend to heaven
to give us the Spirit
to send us out on mission
so that he could move forward
the redemption plan of God.
Read Revelation four and five
this week,
not Matthew 24
if you really want to be encouraged.
I'm just kidding,
do whatever you want
but Revelation four and five,
it's awesome.
So he gives his servants
a tremendous amount of money
and I would argue
the money represents
really two different categories
of giftings
given to us by God.
First is just our individuality,
right?
Like the fact that we have breath
in our lungs,
that we have been given
the gift of life,
this is a massive gift
that we just,
don't fully grasp
on a regular basis
how amazing it is
that we have life
and breath in our lungs
no matter how hard life is for you,
no matter how much struggling
you might be going through,
life is a gift
that you have been given.
Not only that,
you have a vocation,
you have a position in life,
you have a family,
a neighborhood,
a community,
a workplace,
you have been given a gift,
you have a unique personality
with unique abilities,
right?
None of us in this room
are the same,
we all are different,
we've all been given
different gifts
and different abilities
and if you are a follower
of Jesus,
all of those things
have been charged
by the indwelling empowerment
of the Holy Spirit.
What a gift.
Ephesians 2 verse 10,
right?
You are Christ's workmanship
created in Christ Jesus
with good works
that he prepared
in advance for you to do.
Not me to do,
he created some for me to do
but he created some for you to do
and the ones that he created
for you to do,
I can't do
and nobody else can do.
This is a gift,
a massive,
incredible,
amazing gift.
Do not lose sight
of the gift
that God has given you
and do not waste,
listen to this,
do not waste your time
comparing the gifts
that you've been given
to the gifts
that other people
have been given.
It doesn't matter
if you're a five talent,
a two talent,
a one talent,
we're talking gifts,
right?
Let's just go back
to the million dollar illustration.
You're gonna get,
you're gonna be given
a gift of a million dollars
and look at somebody
who has five
and say this sucks.
You didn't deserve
the million to begin with.
It's a free gift.
Tremendous,
incredible generosity
from God
has been given to you.
Do not lose sight of it.
And do not,
do not get stuck
comparing yourself
to others.
God has given you
the gifts he's given you
for your sphere of influence,
for your little bit
of the kingdom.
And this is a good thing.
I,
in my preparation
for sermons
after I do my commentary studies
and I write
my original outline,
I will often search podcasts
and just try and find
other pastors
who have preached the text
to see how they've
incorporated application
to their local congregation.
And I have stumbled
across numbers,
so many pastors
of small churches
all over the country
that none of us
have ever heard of
and I listen to them
preach with power
and authority
and so many of them
are so much better
than I am.
And what I don't do
is think,
that sucks.
I want to be better
than them.
Right?
Praise God
that he has given
the church
gifts of pastors.
And I'm not,
this is not self-deprecating.
I believe that God
has gifted me
and called me
to be doing the thing
that he's calling me to do
but what I do
is I thank him
for the gift
that he's given me
and I praise him
for the gift
that he's given others
especially when he's given
those gifts
that are better.
And I think we need to,
we need,
if we're going to be
faithful followers
of the kingdom,
we've got to have
this attitude.
We've got to be grateful
for the things
that God has given us
and grateful
for the things
that God has given others
even if it is significantly
more than he's given us.
And we cannot look at them
and say they don't deserve that
because it's not up to us.
God chooses
who he gives the gifts to
and why.
Let's be faithful
with what God's given us.
Your neighborhood,
your workplace,
your personality,
your skills,
your education,
your family,
your hobbies,
they are all gifts
that have been given
by God to you
to invest in his kingdom.
The second gift
that he has given each of us
is knowledge of the kingdom.
Not everyone has knowledge
of the kingdom.
Not everyone knows
the realities of God's kingdom
that Jesus,
the Son of God,
came and died
in our place for our sins.
That the creator
of the universe
loves us
and is inviting us
into a relationship with him.
This is the most valuable message
in human history
and you and I
have been entrusted
with it as a gift.
And even if you feel
like you don't know
that much about the Bible,
you don't know
that much about the kingdom,
you know enough.
You know the basics.
You know enough
to take that message forward
to your workplace,
to your neighborhood,
to your coworkers,
your family members,
to your friends.
Some interpreters of this,
the Jewish literature
is packed with symbols
and numbers
meant a lot
in Jewish literature
and so some commentators
have even argued
that five, two, and one,
five represents
the five books of the law,
two represents
the ten tablets
or the two tablets,
Ten Commandments
and one represents God
and so they're almost saying
like hey,
whether you have
a deep, intimate knowledge
of all of God's laws
or you have
a basic understanding
of God
or all you know
is that God loves you,
you have knowledge
of the kingdom
that you can take forward
to others.
So even if you're brand new
to this Jesus thing,
you still have
a tremendous gift
to share.
You know that God loves you
and that he wants
a relationship with you
and that he is in the process
of restoring all creation
to himself
and that's all you need
for now.
Let's keep growing
in knowledge and wisdom
but that is enough
to take to your neighbors,
to your coworkers
and your friends.
Now, this gift,
this generosity,
remember,
it comes with some
responsibility.
N.T. Wright says
this way,
I love it,
he talks about how
the gifts aren't
just our abilities
but also our opportunities.
He says,
the talents are not
simply gifts
of money or abilities
but they are responsibilities
and opportunities
given to us
by the master
and God's kingdom
demands action
and investment
and risk,
not fear
or passivity.
So we have this gift,
it comes with
a responsibility.
The two faithful servants
immediately,
they take the gift
and they put it
to work.
Now, I've got a hunch
that most good Jews
would not be able
to read this parable,
not be able to listen
to this parable
without being thrust back
into the Garden of Eden
narrative.
The master gives
the servant
gifts
to be multiplied,
right?
Do we hear
the Garden of Eden
narrative?
God gives
his image bearers
gifts
and he invites
them to be fruitful
and to multiply
and to fill
the earth
and subdue it.
This is God
replaying,
re-inviting
his people.
Yes,
we screwed up,
Adam and Eve
screwed up
in the Garden of Eden
but God
throughout history
has been re-inviting
his people
back to the same mission.
He is consistent
and faithful
from the beginning
into the end.
He is still
inviting his people
to receive the gifts
that he's given them
and to be fruitful
and to multiply it
and to invest it
in his purposes.
God's character
is consistent
from creation
to the Old Testament
covenants
to the New
Covenant.
The way that
he relates
to his people
is consistent.
He gives us
tremendous gifts
that come with
responsibility
and when we look
at our lives
with this perspective
we realize
there is no such
thing as secular
and sacred.
There is no such
thing as mundane
and meaningful.
Everything we do
is charged
with kingdom
significance.
Whether you're
a student,
a minimum wage
worker,
a cubicle warrior,
stay-at-home parents,
ministry leaders,
whether you have
a disability,
you're a medical
professional,
a teacher,
a business leader,
a retiree,
and on and on
we can go.
Everything you do,
every moment
of your life
is packed
with kingdom
multiplication
opportunities.
Will we get to work
or will we bury
what we've been given?
Kingdom multiplication
requires obedience
but it also requires
risk
and creativity.
I don't know
if you guys
have looked
at the markets
lately.
I don't
because I don't
want to know.
It'll stress me out.
But last time
I checked,
100% return
on investment.
Hard to come by.
Yeah?
Is that accurate?
I don't think
you get 100% return
on investment
without taking
some risks.
Think about Peter
stepping out
into the stormy
waters.
It was a risk
that he was taking
to experience
more of God's kingdom.
Some would say
he's nuts.
what are you doing?
And Jesus says
come on,
come on brother.
Yes,
this is the kind
of faith you have.
You're gonna get
out of the boat.
You're gonna walk
on water.
Come on.
And even
in his risk taking
took a couple
of good steps
and failed,
right?
I just think
Jesus is way
more interested
in obedience
than results.
He's way more
interested in our
willingness to take
the risk
than he is
in the result.
Think about
the little boy
with five loaves
and two fish.
Just obedience.
That's his kid's food.
It's a risk
to offer up
the only thing
he has to eat.
And he puts it
in the hands
of the creator
of the universe
and God
does the
multiplication.
See,
the results
aren't up to us.
The results
are up to God.
The invitation
is obedience.
is stepping out
in faith.
And that
is what's
so darn
sad
about the
unfaithful
servant's response
to one who
has one talent.
It's because
he missed the point.
See,
it was never
about the return.
It was about
the invitation.
the response
to what the
master had
offered him.
And the same
is true
with us.
It's not about
the return.
what we get
done for the
kingdom.
It's about
what we do
in obedience
towards the
kingdom.
Jesus
will deal
with the
results.
We plant
seeds.
I plant it.
Paul is watered.
God gave
the increase.
Kingdom
multiplication
is about
obedience.
We're not
in charge
of the results
and that
should free
us up.
It's a gift.
It comes
with responsibility
and accountability.
In verses
19 through
30,
the master
comes back
and interacts
with his
servants.
He asks
them,
essentially,
what have
you done
with what
I have
given you?
Again,
more garden
imagery.
Right?
Think about
the garden.
God comes
to Adam
and Eve.
He's walking
towards them
in the cool
of day
and they run
and hide
because they
know they
didn't do
the thing
he invited
them to do.
Again,
we're replaying
this imagery.
God has
invited us.
He's given
us gifts.
He's invited
us to
participate
and now
he's coming
back.
And this
will happen.
Jesus
will return
to settle
accounts,
to see what
we've done
with the
gifts that
he's given
us.
God comes
walking to
his image
bearers to
see what
they have
done with
what he
has given.
Jesus
will return
to see
what we
have done
with what
he has
given us.
And if
you're in
here and
you're a
faithful follower
of Jesus,
and when I
say faithful,
I don't mean
perfect.
When I say
faithful,
I don't mean
crushing it.
When I say
faithful,
I might mean
you're barely
keeping your
head above
water but
you're keeping
your eyes
on Jesus.
If you're a
faithful follower
of Jesus,
you should
look forward
to this day
with joyful
anticipation.
This is not
something that
we should be
scared of.
And I don't
know about
you but
sometimes I
can read
these parables,
I can read
this story and
I can think,
oh man,
what am I
going to do
when I have
to stand
before God?
And I just
remind it this
week and I
want to remind
you this week
that if you're
keeping your
eyes on Jesus,
not perfect,
not always
crushing it,
but if you're
entrusting
yourself to
his grace,
to his
kindness,
mercy,
that one
day when you
stand before
him, that
would be a
day of joy,
celebration, it
will not be a
joy, a day
of fear.
And if in
your gut you
have fear about
standing before
God, I feel
like that's
something you
should wrestle
with this
week.
Maybe you
haven't fully
embraced God's
grace or
maybe you just
need to be
reminded of
what it
actually is.
Maybe you've
been raised in
an environment
that told you
God's more
worried about
your results
than your
obedience.
God just
wants you to
be faithful,
he's inviting
you to be
faithful.
We should
look forward
to this day
with joyful
anticipation,
which leads
us to the
unfaithful
servant,
right?
He was not
super looking
forward to
this moment,
he was given
the same
gifts,
opportunities,
and the
same
invitation
as the
other two,
but he
chose to
scorn the
master's
generosity,
to ignore
the
opportunities
and to
reject the
invitation.
The servant
chose selfish
inactivity over
kingdom partnership.
And here's the
thing, we
don't know what
it is, the
story doesn't
tell us what
his motivation
is for doing
this, it
does tell us
what his
excuse is,
and I think
the interaction
he's going to
have with his
master is going
to say that the
excuse that he
came up with
is something
that he
made up, he's
lying to
himself and
to everyone
around him, it's
not true.
We'll get to
the excuse in
just a minute,
but I wonder if
the motivation is
left intentionally
ambiguous because
all of us have
our own motivation
for when we
choose to reject
God's kingdom.
I don't know if
it's personal
autonomy for you,
maybe you just
can't stomach the
idea of anybody
else telling you
what to do.
Americans, we
would never.
But if you're
rejecting God's
invitation because
you want to do
what you want to
do, how you
want to do it,
I'm just here to
tell you it's
exhausting and it
ultimately leads to
you being enslaved
to your own
desires.
You think it's
going to lead to
your joy and
your happiness,
it will not.
It might for a
moment, it might
for a few, but it
ultimately leads to
death and
destruction.
Maybe for you
it's fear or
mistrust.
I don't know if
this master is
good.
I don't know if
I can trust
him.
Maybe it's
competing
allegiances.
You like the
idea of investing
in God's kingdom
but there's so
many other
temporary things
that you enjoy
and you prefer to
invest in those
things first and
foremost and if
you get time for
God's kingdom
then you will.
Maybe it's
entitlement.
You can look at
God's kingdom,
you can see this,
maybe you feel
like you're a
one-talent person,
you see the five
talent people and
the two-talent
people and you're
like God's
God's doing
fine, right?
He's got some
great workers doing
great things for
him.
I'm just gonna,
I'm gonna bow out
of this one.
Again, back to
Ephesians 2.10,
there are good
works created for
you to do that
nobody else can
do.
We've been invited
to participate.
I don't know what
your motivation is.
We don't know what
this servant's
motivation is but we
do know what his
excuse is.
He says you are a
harsh master.
I know that you
gather where you
do not sow.
So I was afraid and
I went and I hid and
as we read this we
could sense like,
okay, maybe the
master is bad.
How do you get
rich, right?
Maybe he is.
And I don't think
that's the point of
the story at all.
As a matter of
fact, I think the
master's interaction
with the servant says
like, hey, the
servant doesn't even
believe this is true.
Right?
He says, if you
believed that I was a
bad master, if you
were really afraid of
me, you would have
put the money in the
bank and then you'd
have something to
show for it.
But I think this guy
uses an excuse that
isn't actually true
just to justify doing
the thing that he
wanted to do to begin
with.
The objections we
have about God often
reveal far more about
our own hearts than
the heart of the
Father.
And I think
sometimes we come
to God with
excuses.
We come to God
with reasons why
we're choosing to
opt out.
And it's not that we
actually believe it's
true about God.
It's just the thing
that we need to tell
ourselves so that we
can keep doing the
thing that we want
to do.
We will tell
ourselves whatever
story we need to
in order to do the
thing that we want
to do.
So, fun stuff this
morning, right?
Awesome.
We've been given a
gift.
That gift comes with
responsibility and
accountability and
ultimately at the end
of the day that
accountability will
either lead to fun
stuff.
You ready?
Joy or judgment.
All of us have been
given gifts.
Life, talents, and
abilities, knowledge of
the kingdom.
And these gifts come
with responsibility and
accountability and
one day we will stand
before God and we
will receive either joy
or judgment.
Joy.
We were given
gifts and the
faithful servants are
given even more
gifts.
They're invited into a
greater responsibility,
a greater opportunity.
And this is like, this
is heaven, this is new
heaven, new earth
imagery.
And so if you grew up
in a church where you
were taught that going
to heaven is like
floating on a cloud or
singing 24-7, like I
think we need to lose
some of that and realize
that the new heaven and
the new earth are going
to invite it to continue
to do the thing that
God has been inviting us
to do from all of
creation, it's going to
be beautiful and
creative, not just lazy
cloud laying.
So if you're looking
forward to lazy cloud
laying, you might be
able to do some of
that, but I don't know
that that's the only
thing on the agenda,
okay?
And it's important here
that we remember our
obedience isn't the
reason that we're
accepted.
accepted, but it is the
only faithful response
to what we've been
given, right?
Like we don't get this
reward because of what
we do, but we do because
of what we've been
given.
And if we realize what
we've been given and we
choose not to do
anything with it, then
maybe we haven't fully
received the gift to
begin with, which leads
to the judgment side of
things.
And I know what some
of you might be
thinking, two weeks in
a row with this weeping
and gnashing of teeth
stuff, come on, trying
to bring my friends to
this church, right?
We don't like judgment.
Seems unfair or too
harsh.
Weeping and gnashing of
teeth, isn't that a bit
much?
Am I the only one in
here?
Thank you.
I appreciate that.
See, I think oftentimes
we read this language of
weeping and gnashing of
teeth and we think about
God sending people away to
a brutal place of sadness
and pain.
We think about God being
the active agent in doing
the judgment.
But how I tend to read it
and how other scholars have
read it throughout human
history is it's the
rebel's response to the
generous invitation.
God's judgment isn't about
his rejection of us, but
about our rejection of
him.
The phrase weeping and
gnashing of teeth is often
used in Scriptures to
describe anger, hostility,
or violence.
It's the person who is
rejecting the generous
offer of the Father, who
continues to reject the
generous offer of the
Father for a number of
motivations with a number
of excuses, but at the
end of the day, they
continually reject God's
generous invitation because
they have a hard heart and
they go willingly into
judgment, angrily into
judgment, gnashing their
teeth at a generous
Father because they have
not received the
generosity, they have not
realized the heart of the
Father towards them.
Judgment is the only
possible outcome for those
who continually reject
God's invitation.
When God's rule and reign
fully comes to earth as it
is in heaven at the second
coming, when heaven and
earth come, when new
heaven and new earth come
and God's rule and reign is
set up eternally on heaven
and earth, that the only
people that can occupy that
space are people that have
willingly submitted to God's
generous offer of invitation
to participate in his
kingdom.
We cannot be in the new
heaven and the new earth if
we are rejecting his
kingdom.
I love how C.S.
Lewis puts it.
He says, there are only two
kinds of people in the end.
Those who say to God, thy
will be done.
And those to whom God says,
in the end, thy will be done.
All that are in hell choose
it.
Without that self-choice,
there could be no hell.
No soul that seriously and
constantly desires joy will
ever miss it.
And those who seek find, and
those who knock, it is
open.
Judgment is far less about
God towards us and far more
about us towards God.
What will we do with the
invitation that we've
received?
Parables meant to stop us in
our tracks, meant to cause us
to rethink everything that
we've ever believed.
And this is a thought-provoking
parable to his disciples as he
is about to leave them and
entrust them with the work of
cultivating God's kingdom until
he returns.
I'd summarize it with this
man.
As ordinary disciples joyfully
invest their God-given gifts and
opportunities wherever they are
placed.
This is the invitation.
We've been given gifts.
We've been given opportunities.
We've been given responsibilities.
And the invitation is to joyfully
invest those things in God's
kingdom purposes.
Not worried about the results,
just worried about the
obedience.
Let God take care of the
results.
Wherever we are placed, whether
you are, whether you love the
spot you're in right now, or
whether you've been begging God
to take you out of the spot
you're in right now, you still
have been given gifts that you
can invest in that opportunity
that you've been placed.
Cool.
I picked this parable for this
day, too, because I think it
has some unique applications to
fathers.
If you're in here and you're a
dad, I just want to say of all
of the gifts that you have been
given, none are more charged with
kingdom potential than your
family.
How are we as fathers, how are we
stewarding that responsibility,
that opportunity?
How are we investing in our
families?
And what multiplication, what
multiplication might God bring
through us raising up a faithful
generation of children who know
that we love them and know that
the Father loves them and know
that they are invited to enter
His joy and participate in
building His kingdom?
You want to talk about 100%
multiplication, 100% return on
investment?
I just can't imagine what God
can do.
Faithful men and women,
fathers and mothers raising up
their children to know that they
are loved by the creator of the
universe.
And that love comes with an
invitation to lay down your life
for your neighbors.
There's this line in the song I try to sing
over my kid on occasion.
And I say try to sing because if you've
heard me sing, it's an effort.
It's a father's blessing and one of the lines
in it says, may our ceiling look like
your floor.
Mom and dad, the highest that we ever
imagine of getting in life and in
faithfulness to God, may that look like
Rory's floor.
May I invest in him and lead him.
May we invest in our children and lead
our children in such a way that our,
the highest thing that we could ever
imagine accomplishing is just their
ceiling, my prayer for our children,
my prayer for our church.
So I'm going to do something that Don
told me not to do because dads don't
like standing up in the middle of
church, but if you're a dad, will you
stand with me?
See, some of you, some of you still are
giving me a look.
I just want to, if we could just extend
our hands to our fathers.
Just pray, Father in heaven, you are the
faithful father.
You are our example.
You are the one true, perfect father.
God, may each one of us as earthly fathers
find our contentment in being loved by
you.
And may we father out of that love.
May we sacrificially serve our families.
May we steward our children towards your
kingdom and may we entrust you with the
results.
We want to steer our kids in the right
direction, but at the end of the day, it
has to be their decision.
And God, we trust you with that.
We're in here and we're brokenhearted.
If there's shame in our hearts because we
feel like failures, God, may you come near
to us and comfort us and encourage us and
remind us that in you there is always
another chance.
May we repent of the ways in which we
failed and may we move towards obedience
and serving our families and our
children.
God, I just pray for encouragement on
these men today.
Pray for energy, for passion, for zeal to
be brought back into their life that they
would realize that the responsibility that
you gave them comes with great joy.
God, do what you want to do in and through
each of these men for your glory and for
their good and for the good of their
families.
In Jesus' name, I pray.
All right, everybody else stand up.
Bail out the dads.
Thank you, men.
I know for some of you that was not fun.
Let me pray this final blessing over each
one of us as we go out to take what the gifts
that we've been given and invest them in
God's kingdom everywhere we find ourselves.
May the God of hope fill you with all joy
and peace as you trust in him so that you
overflow with hope by the power of the
Holy Spirit.
And whatever you do, whatever we do, may
we work at it wholeheartedly as to serving
the Lord, knowing that we will receive an
inheritance from him as our reward.
Go now in joyful faithfulness to the king.
Amen.